I was in New York during Hurricane Sandy,
كنت في نيويورك عند حدوث إعصار ساندي،
and this little white dog called Maui
وكان هذا الجرو الأبيض الصّغير المسمّى
was staying with me.
ماوي كان معي.
Half the city was dark because of a power cut,
كان نصف المدينة مظلما بسبب انقطاع الكهرباء،
and I was living on the dark side.
و كنت أسكن بالجانب المظلم.
Now, Maui was terrified of the dark,
كان ماوي خائفا بسبب الظلام،
so I had to carry him up the stairs,
لذا كان عليّ حمله إلى الطابق فوق،
actually down the stairs first, for his walk,
في الواقع ذهبنا إلى أسفل للتجول به
and then bring him back up.
ثمّ أعدته إلى أعلى.
I was also hauling gallons of bottles of water
كما كنت أحمل غالونات من قوارير المياه
up to the seventh floor every day.
إلى الطابق السابع يوميّا.
And through all of this,
و أثناء كلّ هذا،
I had to hold a torch between my teeth.
كنت مجبرة على حمل مصباح في فمي.
The stores nearby were out of flashlights
لم يكن هناك أضواء في المتاجر
and batteries and bread.
و لا بطاريات أو خبز.
For a shower, I walked 40 blocks
للاستحمام، كان عليّّ المشي مسافة 40 مبنى
to a branch of my gym.
إلى قاعة رياضة.
But these were not the major preoccupations of my day.
لكن هذه لم تكن شواغلي الرئيسية اليومية.
It was just as critical for me to be the first person in
لقد كان عصيبا بالنسبة لي لأكون أول شخص
at a cafe nearby with extension cords and chargers
في مقهى قريب مع امدادات أسلاك و أجهزة الشحن
to juice my multiple devices.
لتغذية آجهزتي المتعدّدة.
I started to prospect under the benches of bakeries
بدأت بالبحث تحت مقاعد المخابز
and the entrances of pastry shops for plug points.
و مداخل محلات المرطبات بحثا عن مقابس.
I wasn't the only one.
لم أكن الوحيدة.
Even in the rain, people stood between Madison and 5th Avenue
حتّى أثناء المطر، كان النّاس واقفين بين شارع ماديسون و الجادة الخامسة
under their umbrellas charging their cell phones
تحت مظلاتهم يشحنون هواتفهم النّقالة
from outlets on the street.
من منافذ كهربائية بالشوارع.
Nature had just reminded us
لقد ذكّرتنا الطبيعة أنّها
that it was stronger than all our technology,
أقوى من كلّ تكنولوجياتنا،
and yet here we were, obsessed about being wired.
و رغم ذلك فنحن لا نزال مهووسين بها.
I think there's nothing like a crisis
أظنّ أنّ ما من أمر كالأزمات
to tell you what's really important and what's not,
لنتعلّم ما المهم حقا و ما ليس كذلك،
and Sandy made me realize that our devices
و ساندي جعلنا ندرك أنّ آلاتنا
and their connectivity matter to us
و اتصالها هي أمور هامة لنا
right up there with food and shelter.
كأهمية الغذاء و المأوى.
The self as we once knew it no longer exists,
الذات كما كنّا نعرفها لم تعد موجودة،
and I think that an abstract, digital universe
أعتقد أنّ هناك كونا تجريديّا رقميّا
has become a part of our identity,
قد أصبح يمثّل جزءا من هويّتنا،
and I want to talk to you about what I think that means.
و أرغب في التّحدث عن معنى ذلك في رأيي.
I'm a novelist, and I'm interested in the self
أنا كاتبة، أنا مهتمّة بالذات،
because the self and fiction have a lot in common.
لأنّها تتشارك في عديد الأمور مع الخيال.
They're both stories, interpretations.
كلاهما قصة و تأويل.
You and I can experience things without a story.
نحن نستطيع المرور بتجارب دون الحاجة إلى قصة.
We might run up the stairs too quickly
قد نركض نحو أعلى الدّرج بسرعة
and we might get breathless.
و نبدأ باللّهيث.
But the larger sense that we have of our lives,
لكن ادراكنا لحياتنا، الذي يكون في العادة
the slightly more abstract one, is indirect.
أكثر تجريديّة، هو غير مباشر.
Our story of our life is based on direct experience,
قصصنا الحياة مبنيّة على تجارب مباشرة،
but it's embellished.
لكنّها مزيّنة.
A novel needs scene after scene to build,
الرواية تحتاج المشهد متبوعا بمشهد آخر حتّى تُنبنى،
and the story of our life needs an arc as well.
و الأمر مشابه بالنّسبة لحياتنا.
It needs months and years.
إنّها تحتاج أشهرا و سنوات.
Discrete moments from our lives are its chapters.
اللّحظات المنفصلة من حيواتنا هي بمثابة الفصول.
But the story is not about these chapters.
لكن القصة لا تتمحور حول هذه الفصول.
It's the whole book.
بل الكتاب كله.
It's not only about the heartbreak and the happiness,
لا يتعلّق الأمر بالألم أو السعادة،
the victories and the disappointments,
النّجاحات و الفشل،
but it's because how because of these,
بل بكيفيّة أنّ كل ذلك،
and sometimes, more importantly, in spite of these,
و في بعض الأحيان بالرغم من ذلك،
we find our place in the world
نحن نجد أماكننا في العالم
and we change it and we change ourselves.
و نغيّره و نغيّر أنفسنا.
Our story, therefore, needs two dimensions of time:
قصصنا بالتّلي تحتاج بعدين من الزّمن:
a long arc of time that is our lifespan,
قوس طويل من الزّمن وهو العمر،
and the timeframe of direct experience
و الإطار الزّمني للتجربة المباشرة
that is the moment.
أي اللّحظة الآنيّة.
Now the self that experiences directly
الذات القادرة على الاحساس مباشرة
can only exist in the moment,
هي بالضرورة ذات تعيش في اللحظة،
but the one that narrates needs several moments,
لكن الذات التي تروي، تحتاج بعض لحظات
a whole sequence of them,
مجموعة كاملة منها،
and that's why our full sense of self
ولهذا فإنّ ادراكنا للنّفس
needs both immersive experience
يحتاج خبرة كبيرة
and the flow of time.
و مرور الزّمن.
Now, the flow of time is embedded in everything,
مرور الزّمن موجود في كلّ شيء،
in the erosion of a grain of sand,
في تعرية حبات الرمل،
in the budding of a little bud into a rose.
في تبرعم البرعم الصغير الي وردة
Without it, we would have no music.
وبدون ذلك، سيكون لدينا لا الموسيقى.
Our own emotions and state of mind
حالتنا الذهنية و مشاعرنا الخاصة بنا
often encode time,
و غالبا ترميز الوقت
regret or nostalgia about the past,
الندم أو الحنين إلى الماضي،
hope or dread about the future.
الأمل أو الفزع إزاء المستقبل.
I think that technology has altered that flow of time.
وأعتقد أن التكنولوجيا قد غيرت هذا التدفق من الوقت.
The overall time that we have for our narrative,
الوقت الإجمالي التي لدينا بالنسبة لنا السرد،
our lifespan, has been increasing,
العمر الافتراضي لدينا قد تمت زيادته
but the smallest measure, the moment, has shrunk.
لكن مقياس أصغر، اللحظة , قد تقلصت
It has shrunk because our instruments enable us
قد تقلصت لأن أدواتنا تمكننا من ذلك
in part to measure smaller and smaller units of time,
في جزء قياس وحدات أصغر وأصغر من الوقت،
and this in turn has given us a more granular understanding
وهذا بدوره قد أعطانا فهم محبوب اكثر
of the material world,
من العالم المادي،
and this granular understanding
وهذا الفهم المحبوب
has generated reams of data
قد ولد كما من البيانات
that our brains can no longer comprehend
لا تستطيع عقولنا ادراكه
and for which we need more and more complicated computers.
وبالتالي نحن بحاجة إلى أجهزة الكمبيوتر أكثر وأكثر تعقيداً.
All of this to say that the gap
كل هذا القول بأن الفجوة
between what we can perceive and what we can measure
بين ما يمكن أن نعتبره وما يمكن أن نقيس
is only going to widen.
لن يؤدي إلا توسيع.
Science can do things with and in a picosecond,
العلم يمكنه القيام بأشياء معه وفي بيكو ثانية ،
but you and I are never going to have the inner experience
ولكن أنت وأنا لن يكون لدينا الخبرة الداخلية ابدا
of a millionth of a millionth of a second.
من مليون المليون من الثانية.
You and I answer only to nature's rhythm and flow,
أنا وأنت تجيب فقط لإيقاع الطبيعة و التدفق
to the sun, the moon and the seasons,
للشمس والقمر والفصول،
and this is why we need that long arc of time
و هذا لماذا نحن بحوجة لدلك القوس الطويل من الزمن
with the past, the present and the future
مع الماضي والحاضر والمستقبل
to see things for what they are,
لرؤية الأمور على حقيقتها،
to separate signal from noise
لفصل إشارة من الضوضاء
and the self from sensations.
والنفس من الأحاسيس.
We need time's arrow to understand cause and effect,
نحن بحاجة إلى السهم للوقت فهم السبب والنتيجة،
not just in the material world,
ليس فقط في العالم المادي،
but in our own intentions and our motivations.
ولكن في منطقتنا النوايا والدوافع لدينا.
What happens when that arrow goes awry?
ماذا يحدث عندما يعوج هذا السهم ؟
What happens when time warps?
ماذا يحدث عند اعوجاج الوقت ؟
So many of us today have the sensation
الكثير منا اليوم لديهم الإحساس
that time's arrow is pointing everywhere
يشير السهم في ذلك الوقت في كل مكان
and nowhere at once.
ولا مكان في وقت واحد.
This is because time doesn't flow in the digital world
وهذا يرجع إلى أن الوقت لا تتدفق في العالم الرقمي
in the same way that it does in the natural one.
في نفس الطريق لا أنه في واحد الطبيعية.
We all know that the Internet has shrunk space
وكلنا نعلم أن الإنترنت قد تقلصت مساحة
as well as time.
فضلا عن الوقت.
Far away over there is now here.
بعيداً أكثر من هناك الآن هنا.
News from India is a stream on my smartphone app
أخبار من الهند تيار في بلدي التطبيق الذكي
whether I'm in New York or New Delhi.
وأنا سواء في نيويورك أو نيو دلهي.
And that's not all.
وهذا ليس كل شيء.
Your last job, your dinner reservations from last year,
وظيفتك السابقة، حجوزات العشاء الخاص بك من العام الماضي،
your former friends, lie on a flat plain with today's friends,
أصدقائك السابقين، كذب على سهل مسطح مع أصدقاء اليوم،
because the Internet also archives,
لأن المحفوظات الإنترنت أيضا،
and it warps the past.
وهو اﻻعوجاج في الماضي.
With no distinction left between the past,
مع تمييز لا تترك بين الماضي،
the present and the future, and the here or there,
في الوقت الحاضر وفي المستقبل، وهنا أو هناك،
we are left with this moment everywhere,
ونحن مع هذه اللحظة في كل مكان، ترك
this moment that I'll call the digital now.
هذه اللحظة التي سوف اسمية الرقمية الآن.
Just how can we prioritize
كيف يمكن أن نعطي الأولوية
in the landscape of the digital now?
في المناظر الطبيعية الرقمية الآن؟
This digital now is not the present,
هذا الرقمي الآن ليس الوقت الحاضر،
because it's always a few seconds ahead,
لأنها دائماً بضع ثوان قدما،
with Twitter streams that are already trending
مع تيارات التغريد التي هي فعلا تتجه
and news from other time zones.
والأنباء الواردة من مناطق زمنية أخرى.
This isn't the now of a shooting pain in your foot
هذا ليس الآن لإطلاق النار ألم في قدمك
or the second that you bite into a pastry
أو الثانية أن كنت لدغة في الحلويات
or the three hours that you lose yourself in a great book.
أو الثلاث ساعات أن تفقد نفسك في كتاب عظيم.
This now bears very little physical
ويتحمل هذا الآن المادي القليل جداً
or psychological reference to our own state.
أو مرجع النفسية لحالتنا
Its focus, instead, is to distract us
تركيزه، بدلا من , ان يشتت انتباهنا
at every turn on the road.
عند كل منعطف على الطريق.
Every digital landmark is an invitation
كل معلم مميز رقمي و دعوة
to leave what you are doing now to go somewhere else
لترك ما تقوم به الآن و الذهاب إلى مكان آخر
and do something else.
وتفعل شيئا آخر.
Are you reading an interview by an author?
يمكنك قراءة مقابلة أجراها مؤلف ؟
Why not buy his book? Tweet it. Share it.
لماذا لا تشتري كتابه ؟ غرده . انشره .
Like it. Find other books exactly like his.
حبها . اعثر على كتب أخرى بالضبط مثل كتبه.
Find other people reading those books.
جد اشخاصا اخرين يقرؤون تلك الكنب
Travel can be liberating,
السفر يمكن ان يكون محرر
but when it is incessant, we become
ولكن عندما يكون مستمر ، نصبح
permanent exiles without repose.
المغتربون دائما و من دون راحة
Choice is freedom, but not when it's constantly
والخيار هو الحرية، ولكن ليست عندما تكون دائمة
for its own sake.
من اجلها هي
Not just is the digital now far from the present,
هو ليس فقط الرقمية الآن أبعد ما تكون عن الحاضر،
but it's in direct competition with it,
ولكن في منافسة مباشرة مع ذلك،
and this is because not just am I absent from it,
وهذا ليس بسبب أني غائبة منها فقط،
but so are you.
ولكن حتى أنت.
Not just are we absent from it, but so is everyone else.
ليس فقط نحن الغائبين من ذلك، ولكن ذلك كل شخص آخر.
And therein lies its greatest convenience and horror.
وهنا يكمن أكبر قدر من الراحة والرعب.
I can order foreign language books in the middle of the night,
يمكن أن أطلب كتب باللغة الأجنبية في منتصف الليل،
shop for Parisian macarons,
متجر ماكارونس الباريسي،
and leave video messages that get picked up later.
وترك رسائل الفيديو التي سيتم الحصول عليها لاحقا .
At all times, I can operate
في جميع الأوقات، يمكن أن تعمل
at a different rhythm and pace from you,
في إيقاع مختلف وخطي منك،
while I sustain the illusion
وبينما أنا اتحمل الوهم
that I'm tapped into you in real time.
أنني داعبت في الوقت الحقيقي
Sandy was a reminder
ساندي كانت تذكرة
of how such an illusion can shatter.
من كيفية و امكان ان يتحطم الوهم
There were those with power and water,
كان هناك من يملك الطاقة والمياه
and those without.
والذين لا يملكون.
There are those who went back to their lives,
وهناك أولئك الذين عادوا إلى حياتهم،
and those who are still displaced
وأولئك الذين هم ما زالوا مشردين
after so many months.
بعد أشهر عديدة.
For some reason, technology seems to perpetuate
لسبب ما، يبدو التكنولوجيا خالدة
the illusion for those who have it that everyone does,
الوهم لأولئك الذين لديهم , يفعل ذلك الجميع،
and then, like an ironic slap in the face,
وبعد ذلك، مثل المفارقات صفعة في الوجه،
it makes it true.
يجعله صحيحاً.
For example, it's said that there are more people
على سبيل المثال، يقال أن هناك المزيد من الناس
in India with access to cell phones than toilets.
في الهند مع الوصول إلى الهواتف المحمولة من المراحيض.
Now if this rift, which is already so great
الآن إذا كان هذا الصدع، الذي هو بالفعل كبيرة جداً
in many parts of the world,
في أجزاء كثيرة من العالم،
between the lack of infrastructure and the spread of technology,
بين الافتقار إلى البنية التحتية وانتشار التكنولوجيا،
isn't somehow bridged,
ليس سدها بطريقة ما،
there will be ruptures between the digital
وسوف يكون هناك تصدعات بين الرقمية
and the real.
والحقيقية.
For us as individuals who live in the digital now
بالنسبة لنا كالأفراد الذين يعيشون في الرقمية الآن
and spend most of our waking moments in it,
وتنفق معظم لحظات الاستيقاظ لدينا في ذلك،
the challenge is to live in two streams of time
والتحدي أن نعيش في اثنان التدفقات الزمنية
that are parallel and almost simultaneous.
المتوازية و المتشابهة تقريبا
How does one live inside distraction?
كيف يمكن لأحد العيش داخل الالهاء ؟
We might think that those younger than us,
وقد نفكر أن أولئك الأصغر سنا أكثر منا،
those who are born into this, will adapt more naturally.
أولئك الذين يولدون في هذا، وسوف يتكيفون أكثر بطبيعة الحال.
Possibly, but I remember my childhood.
ربما، ولكن أنا أتذكر طفولتي.
I remember my grandfather revising
وأتذكر جدي تراجع
the capitals of the world with me.
عواصم العالم معي
Buda and Pest were separated by the Danube,
تم فصل بودا و بست من نهر الدانوب،
and Vienna had a Spanish riding school.
وكانت فيينا مدرسة ركوب الخيل الإسبانية.
If I were a child today, I could easily learn this information
إذا كان طفل اليوم، أنا يمكن بسهولة التعرف على هذه المعلومات
with apps and hyperlinks,
مع الارتباطات التشعبية، والتطبيقات
but it really wouldn't be the same,
ولكننها حقاً لن تكون هي نفسها،
because much later, I went to Vienna,
لأن الكثير في وقت لاحق، ذهبت إلى فيينا،
and I went to the Spanish riding school,
وذهبت إلى مدرسة الفروسية الإسبانية،
and I could feel my grandfather right beside me.
ويمكن أن أشعر بحدي جواري .
Night after night, he took me up on the terrace,
ليلة بعد ليلة، اخذني الي اعلي الشرفة،
on his shoulders, and pointed out Jupiter
على الكتفين، وأشار إلى كوكب المشتري
and Saturn and the Great Bear to me.
وكوكب زحل والدب الكبرى بالنسبة لي.
And even here, when I look at the Great Bear,
وحتى هنا، عندما انظر الي الدب الكبرى،
I get back that feeling of being a child,
احصل على شعور العودة الي كوني طفلة،
hanging onto his head and trying to balance myself
متشبثة على رأسه و احاول ان اوازن نفسي
on his shoulder,
في كتفه،
and I can get back that feeling of being a child again.
ويمكنني استرجاع ذاك الشعور كطفلة مرة أخرى.
What I had with my grandfather was wrapped
ما كان لي مع جدي كانت ملفوفة
so often in information and knowledge and fact,
لذا في كثير من الأحيان في المعلومات والمعرفة والحقيقة،
but it was about so much more
ولكن كان حول أكثر من ذلك بكثير
than information or knowledge or fact.
من المعلومات أو المعرفة أو الحقيقة.
Time-warping technology challenges
تحديات التكنولوجيا تزييفها في الوقت
our deepest core,
أعمالنا الأساسية أعمق،
because we are able to archive the past
لأننا قادرون على أرشفة الماضي
and some of it becomes hard to forget,
وبعض منه لأنه يصبح من الصعب أن ننسى،
even as the current moment
حتى كهذه اللحظة الراهنة
is increasingly unmemorable.
هو في زيادة لا يمكن تذكره .
We want to clutch, and we are left instead
ونحن نريد أن نقبض ، و لكن غادرنا من دون ذلك
clutching at a series of static moments.
نقبض سلسلة من اللحظات ثابتة.
They're like soap bubbles that disappear when we touch them.
أنهم مثل فقاعات الصابون التي تختفي عندما نلمسها .
By archiving everything, we think that we can store it,
بأرشفة كل شيء، نحن نعتقد أنه يمكننا تخزينها،
but time is not data.
ولكن الوقت ليس البيانات.
It cannot be stored.
لا يمكن تخزينه .
You and I know exactly what it means like
و انا و انت نعرف بالضبط ما يعنيه
to be truly present in a moment.
ليكون حاضرا حقاً في لحظة.
It might have happened while we were
قد يكون قد حدث بينما كنا
playing an instrument,
نلعب آلة موسيقية،
or looking into the eyes of someone we've known
أو نبحث في عيون شخص ما نحن على علم
for a very long time.
لفترة طويلة جداً.
At such moments, our selves are complete.
في مثل هذه اللحظات، ذواتنا كاملة.
The self that lives in the long narrative arc
النفس التي تعيش في القوس السرد الطويل
and the self that experiences the moment
والنفس التي تمر بالخبرات في الوقت الحالي
become one.
تصبح واحدة.
The present encapsulates the past
يغليف الحاضر الماضي
and a promise for the future.
ووعد في المستقبل.
The present joins a flow of time
الوقت الحاضر تضم صوتها إلى تدفق من الوقت
from before and after.
من قبل وبعد.
I first experienced these feelings with my grandmother.
أولاً لقد واجهت هذه المشاعر مع جدتي.
I wanted to learn to skip, and she found an old rope
أردت أن اتعلم لاتخطي ، وقالت أنها وجدت حبلا قديما
and she tucked up her sari
و انها طوت ذلك الساري الذي يخصها
and she jumped over it.
و أنها قفزت من فوقه .
I wanted to learn to cook, and she kept me in the kitchen,
أردت أن اتعلم طهي الطعام، و قد جعلتني ابقى في المطبخ،
cutting, cubing and chopping for a whole month.
قطع والتكعيب وتقطيع لمدة شهر كامل.
My grandmother taught me that things happen
علمتني جدتي أن الأمور
in the time they take, that time can't be fought,
في الوقت الذي يأخذونه، ذاك الوقت لا يمكن مقاتلته،
and because it will pass and it will move,
ونظرا لأنه سيتم تمرير وأنها سوف تتحرك،
we owe the present moment our full attention.
ونحن ندين هذه اللحظة اهتمامنا الكامل.
Attention is time.
الاهتمام هو الوقت.
One of my yoga instructors once said
وقال أحد مدربي اليوغا لي مرة
that love is attention,
أن الحب هو الاهتمام،
and definitely from my grandmother,
وقطعا من جدتي،
love and attention were one and the same thing.
الحب والاهتمام من واحد ونفس الشيء.
The digital world cannibalizes time,
العالم الرقمي يفكك الوقت،
and in doing so, I want to suggest
وفي قيامها بذلك، أود أن اقترح
that what it threatens
أن ما كان يهدد
is the completeness of ourselves.
هو الكمال لأنفسنا.
It threatens the flow of love.
وهو يهدد تدفق الحب.
But we don't need to let it.
ولكن لسنا بحاجة للسماح لها.
We can choose otherwise.
يمكننا أن نختار ما هو خلاف ذلك.
We've seen again and again
لقد شهدنا مرارا وتكرارا
just how creative technology can be,
كيف يمكن أن كون التكنولوجيا عبقرية،
and in our lives and in our actions,
وفي حياتنا وفي أعمالنا،
we can choose those solutions and those innovations
وبوسعنا أن نختار تلك الحلول وتلك الابتكارات
and those moments that restore the flow of time
وتلك اللحظات التي تستعيد تدفق الوقت
instead of fragmenting it.
بدلاً من تفتيت عليه.
We can slow down and we can tune in
ونحن يمكن أن تبطئ ونحن يمكن أن تصل قيمتها
to the ebb and flow of time.
إلى انحسار وتدفق من الوقت.
We can choose to take time back.
يمكننا أن نختار لنأخذ الوقت إلى الوراء.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)